So I really consider myself a storyteller.
أنا أعتبر نفسي راوي قصص.
But I don't really tell stories in the usual way,
لكني لا أروي القصص بالطريقة العادية،
in the sense that I don't usually tell my own stories.
بمعنى أنني لا أروي في العادة قصصي الخاصة.
Instead, I'm really interested in building tools that allow
بدلاً عن ذلك، أنا مهتم ببناء أدوات تسمح
large numbers of other people to tell their stories,
لعدد كبير من الناس الآخرين ليرووا قصصهم،
people all around the world.
ناس من كل أنحاء العالم.
I do this because I think that people actually have a lot in common.
أفعل هذا لأنني أعتقد أن هنالك الكثير من الأشياء المشتركة بين الناس.
I think people are very similar,
أعتقد أن الناس متشابهون جداً،
but I also think that we have trouble seeing that.
لكني أعتقد أيضاً أن لدينا مشكلة في رؤية ذلك.
You know, as I look around the world I see a lot of gaps,
تعرفون، عندما أنظر حول العالم أرى فروقاً كثيرة،
and I think we all see a lot of gaps.
وأعتقد أننا جميعاً نرى الكثير من الفروق.
And we define ourselves by our gaps.
ونعرف أنفسنا بواسطة هذه الفروقات.
There's language gaps,
تعرفون، هناك فروق لغوية،
there's ethnicity and racial gaps, there's age gaps,
هناك فروق إثنية وعنصرية، هناك فوارق عمرية،
there's gender gaps, there's sexuality gaps,
هناك فوارق نوع، هناك فوارق جنسية،
there's wealth and money gaps, there's education gaps,
هناك فوارق ثروة ومال، هناك فوارق تعليمية،
there's also religious gaps.
هناك فوارق دينية أيضاً.
You know, we have all these gaps and I think we like our gaps
تعرفون، لدينا كل هذه الفروقات وأعتقد أننا نحب فوارقنا
because they make us feel like we identify with something,
لأنها تجعلنا نحس بأنها هويتنا مع شئ،
some smaller community.
مجتمع أصغر.
But I think that actually, despite our gaps,
لكني أعتقد أن ذلك في الواقع، رغماً عن فوارقنا،
we really have a lot in common.
لدينا الكثير من المشترك حقاً.
And I think one thing we have in common is a very deep need
وأعتقد أن أحد الأشياء التي نشترك فيها هي الحوجة الماسة
to express ourselves.
للتعبير عن أنفسنا.
I think this is a very old human desire. It's nothing new.
أعتقد أن هذه رغبة إنسانية قديمة جداً. وليست شئ جديد.
But the thing about self-expression
لكن الأمر حول التعبير عن النفس
is that there's traditionally been this imbalance
هو أنه كان غير متوازن تقليدياً
between the desire that we have to express ourselves
بين الرغبة التي لدينا للتعبير عن أنفسنا
and the number of sympathetic friends
وعدد الأصدقاء المتعاطفين
who are willing to stand around and listen.
الذين يرغبون بالمساندة والسماع.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This, also, is nothing new.
هذا، أيضاً، ليس شيئاً جديداً.
Since the dawn of human history, we've tried to rectify this imbalance
منذ فجر تاريخ البشرية، حاولنا تصحيح هذا الخلل
by making art, writing poems, singing songs,
بصنع الفن، كتابة القصائد، أدأ الأغنيات،
scripting editorials and sending them in to a newspaper,
تحرير النصوص وإرسالها الى الصحف،
gossiping with friends. This is nothing new.
النميمة مع الأصدقاء. وهذا ليس جديداً.
What's new is that in the last several years
الشئ الجديد هو أنه في السنوات الأخيرة
a lot of these very traditional physical human activities,
الكثير من هذه الأنشطة البشرية التقليدية،
these acts of self-expression, have been moving onto the Internet.
هذه التصرفات للتعبير عن النفس، أنتقلت الى الإنترنت.
And as that's happened, people have been leaving behind footprints,
ولأن هذا حدث، ظل الناس يتركون بصمات خلفهم،
footprints that tell stories of their moments of self-expression.
بصمات تروي قصصاً للحظات التعبير عن ذواتهم.
And so what I do is, I write computer programs
وإذاً، ما أفعله هو، أكتب برامج كمبيوتر
that study very large sets of these footprints,
تدرس مجموعة ضخمة من هذه البصمات،
and then try to draw conclusions about the people who left them --
وبعد ذلك تحاول رسم خلاصات حول الناس الذين تركوها--
what they feel, what they think,
بماذا يشعرون، ماذا يفكرون،
what's different in the world today than usual,
ما هو الفرق للعالم اليوم عن الأيام المعتادة.
these sorts of questions.
هذا النوع من الأسئلة.
One project that explores these ideas,
مشروعنا الذي يستكشف هذه الأفكار،
which was made about a year ago,
الذي أنجزناه قبل حوالي سنة مضت،
is a piece called We Feel Fine.
يسمى نشعر بتحسن.
This is a piece that every two or three minutes
هذا البرنامج يقوم كل دقيقتين أو ثلاثة
scans the world's newly-posted blog entries
بمسح المداخلات الجديدة من عالم المدونات
for occurrences of the phrases "I feel" or "I am feeling."
لظهور المقاطع "أشعر" أو " أنا أشعر".
And when it finds one of those phrases,
وعندما يجد أحد تلك الفقرات،
it grabs the sentence up to the period,
يجلب الجملة لكل الفترة الزمنية،
and then automatically tries to deduce the age, gender
ومن ثم يحاول تلقائيا الإستدلال على العمر والجنس،
and geographical location of the person that wrote that sentence.
والمكان الجغرافي لذلك الشخص الذي كتب الجملة.
Then, knowing the geographical location and the time,
بعد ذلك، بمعرفة المكان الجغرافي والزمن،
we can also then figure out the weather
يمكننا أيضاً معرفة الطقس
when that person wrote the sentence.
عندما كتب ذلك الشخص الجملة.
All of this information is saved in a database
كل هذه المعلومات يتم حفظها في قاعدة بيانات
that collects about 20,000 feelings a day.
تقوم بتجميع حوالي 20 ألف شعور يومياً.
It's been running for about a year and a half.
يعمل هذا لحوالي سنة ونصف.
It's reached about seven-and-a-half million human feelings now.
لقد بلغ حوالي سبعة ونصف شعوراً إنسانياً الآن،
And I'll show you a glimpse
وسأريكم لمحة
of how this information is then visualized. So this is We Feel Fine.
لكيف يتم جعل هذه المعلومات مرئية. إذاً هذا هو "نشعر بتحسن".
What you see here is a madly swarming mass of particles,
ما تشاهدونه هنا هو كتلة محتشدة بالجزيئات ،
each of which represents a single human feeling
كل منها يمثل شعوراً واحداً لشخص
that was stated in the last few hours.
ورد ذلك خلال الساعات القليلة الماضية.
The color of each particle corresponds to the type of feeling inside --
لون كل جزئ يمثل نوع من المشاعر في الداخل --
so that happy, positive feelings are brightly colored.
إذاً ذلك سعيد، المشاعر الإيجابية تظهر باللون الفاتح.
And sad, negative feelings are darkly colored.
و حزين، المشاعر السالبة تظهر باللون الغامض.
The diameter of each dot
نصف قطر كل نقطة
represents the length of the sentence inside,
تمثل طول الجملة في الداخل،
so that the large dots contain large sentences,
وتلك النقاط الكبيرة تحوي جملاً طويلة،
and the small dots contain small sentences.
والنقاط الصغيرة تحوي جملاً قصيرة.
Any dot can be clicked and expanded. And we see here,
يمكن الضغط على كل نقطة تقبل وتتمدد. ويمكنك رؤية ذلك هنا،
"I would just feel so much better
" أريد أن أشعر بتحسن كثير
if I could curl up in his arms right now and feel his affection for me
اذا كنت بين ذراعيه الآن وأشعر بحبه لي
in the embrace of his body and the tenderness of his lips."
في حضن من جسده والحنان من شفتيه."
So it gets pretty hot and steamy sometimes
إذاً تصبح أكثر إثارة وإغراء بعض الأحيان
in the world of human emotions.
في عالم المشاعر الإنسانية.
And all of these are stated by people:
وكل ذلك صرح به الناس:
"I know that objectively it really doesn't mean much,
" أعرف أن الموضوعية لا تعني الكثير،
but after spending so many years as a small fish in a big pond,
لكن بعد قضاء العديد من السنين كسمكة صغيرة في بركة كبيرة،
it's nice to feel bigger again."
من الجيد أن تشعر بالكبر مجدداً."
The dots exhibit human qualities. They kind of have their own physics,
النقاط تعكس جودة الإنسان. أنهم نوعاً ما لديهم أنشطتهم الخاصة،
and they swarm wildly around, kind of exploring the world of life.
أنهم ينسابون بتهور، نوع من استكشاف فضاءات الحياة.
And then they also exhibit curiosity.
وبعد ذلك أيضاً يعرضون الفضول.
You can see a few of them are swarming around the cursor right now.
يمكنكم رؤية القليل منها تنساب حول المؤشر الآن.
You can see some other ones
يمكنك رؤية بعض الأشياء الأخرى
are swarming around the bottom left corner of the screen
تنساب حول أسفل الزاوية اليسرى من الشاشة
around six words. Those six words represent the six movements
حوالي ستة كلمات. تلك الكلمات الستة تمثل الحركات الست
of We Feel Fine. We're currently seeing Madness.
لبرنامج "نشعر بتحسن". نشاهد حالياً الغضب .
There's also Murmurs, Montage, Mobs, Metrics and Mounds.
هناك أيضا الدندنة ، مونتاج ، الغوغاء ، القياسات وتلال .
And I'll walk you through a few of those now.
وسآخذكم حول القليل منها الآن.
Murmurs causes all of the feelings to fly to the ceiling.
الغوغاء تسبب المشاعر للتحليق الى السقف.
And then, one by one, in reverse chronological order,
وبعد ذلك، واحدة تلو الأخرى، بترتيب زمني معكوس،
they excuse themselves, entering the scrolling list of feelings.
يعذرون أنفسهم، بالدخول في قائمة دائرية للمشاعر.
"I feel a bit better now."
" أشعر بتحسن قليل الآن."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"I feel confused and unsure of what the hell I want to do."
"أشعر بالإرتباك ولست متأكد ماذا سأفعل."
"I feel gypped out of something awesome here."
"أشعر أنني أسرت بشئ رائع هنا."
"I feel so free; I feel so good."
" أشعر أنني طليق السراح. أشعر بتحسن كبير."
"I feel like I'm in this fog of depression that I can't get out of."
" أشعر أنني في هذا الضباب الكئيب بحيث لا أستطيع الخلاص منه."
And you can click any of these to go out and visit the blog
ويمكنك الضغط على أي من هذه لتذهب الى المدونة
from which it was collected. And in that way,
التي جمعنا منها ذلك. وبتلك الطريقة،
you can connect with the authors of these statements
يمكنك التواصل مع المؤلفين لتلك الجمل،
if you feel some degree of empathy.
اذا شعرت بنوع ما من التعاطف.
The next movement is called Montage.
الحركة التالية تسمى مونتاج.
Montage causes all of the feelings that contain photographs
مونتاج تنتج من كل المشاعر التي تحوي صوراً
to become extracted and display themselves in a grid.
ليتم إستخلاصها وعرضها في شبكة.
This grid is then said to represent the picture of the world's feelings
هذه الشبكة يقال أنها تمثل الصورة لعالم المشاعر
in the last few hours, if you will.
في الخمس ساعات الأخيرة، اذا شئتم.
Each of these can be clicked and we can blow it up.
أي من هذه يمكن الضغط عليها ويمكن قراءتها.
We see, "I just feel like I'm not going to have fun
نشاهد، " أشعر بأنني لن أستمتع
if it's not the both of us." That was from someone in Michigan.
اذا لم يكن كلانا." كان ذلك من شخص ما في ميتشغان.
We see, "I feel like I have been at a computer all day."
نشاعد، " أشعر أنني أجلس على الكمبيوتر طوال اليوم."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
These are automatically constructed using the found objects:
كل هذه تم بناؤها تلقائياً بواسطة الأشياء التي يعثر عليها
"I think I feel a little full."
"أشعر أنني شبعان قليلاً."
The next movement is called mobs.
المرحلة التالية تسمى الغوغاء.
Mobs provides different statistical breakdowns
الغوغاء تقدم مختلف أعطال الإحصاء
of the population of the world's feelings in the last few hours.
لعالم المشاعر في الساعات القليلة الفائتة.
We see that "better" is the most frequent feeling right now,
نشاهد أن "أفضل" هي أكثر المشاعر تكراراً الآن،
followed by "good," "bad," "guilty," "right," "down," "sick" and so on.
يعقبها جيد، سيئ، مذنب، يمين، أسفل، مريض والخ.
We can also get a gender breakdown.
يمكنك أيضاً الحصول على تفصيل بين الجنسين.
And we see that women are slightly more prolific
ونحن نرى أن النساء هن أكثر قليلا إنتاجاً
talking about their emotions in the last few hours than men.
في الحديث عن مشاعرهن في الساعات الأخيرة عن الرجال.
We can do an age breakdown, which gives us a histogram
يمكن الحصول على تفضيل للأعمار، الذي يعطينا رسم بياني
of the world's emotional distribution by age.
لتوزيع عالم المشاعر بالأعمار.
We see people in their twenties are the most prolific,
نرى أن الناس في أعمار العشرينيات أكثر إنتاجاً،
followed by teenagers, and then people in their thirties,
يعقبهم المراهقون، وبعد ذلك الناس في الثلاثينيات،
and it dies out very quickly from there.
وينخفض الأمر بسرعة من هناك.
In weather, the feelings assume the physical characteristics
في الطقس، تحمل المشاعر الصفات الفيزيائية
of the weather that they represent,
للطقس الذي يمثلونه،
so that the ones collected on a sunny day
بحيث تكون تلك المجمعة في يوم مشمس
swirl around as if they're part of the sun.
يدور حول شئ مثل أنه جزء من الشمس.
The cloudy ones float along as if they're on a breeze.
تلك الملبدة بالغيوم تطفو كما لو أنهم على النسيم.
The rainy ones fall down as if they're in a rainstorm,
تلك الممطرة تقع في الأسفل كما لو أنهم في عاصفة ممطرة،
and the snowy ones kind of flutter to the ground.
و النوع الثلجي يرفرف على أرض الواقع.
Finally, location causes the feelings to move to their positions
أخيراً، يسبب المكان تحريك المشاعر لأوضاعهم
on a world map showing the geographical distribution of feelings.
في خارطة العالم مظهرة التوزيع الجغرافي للمشاعر.
Metrics provides more numerical views on the data.
توفر القياسات نظرة رقمية أكثر حول البيانات.
We see that the world is feeling "used"
نرى أن العالم يستخدم مشاعراً
at 3.3 times the normal level right now.
أكثر ب 3.3 مرة من المستوى العادي الآن.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
They're feeling "warm" at 2.9 times the normal level, and so on.
يشعرون بالدفء 2.9 مرة من المستوى العادي ، والخ.
Other views are also available.
توجد لمحات أخرى أيضاً .
Here are gender, age, weather, location.
هنا النوع، العمر، الطقس، المكان.
The final movement is called Mounds.
الحركة الأخيرة تسمى تلال .
It's a bit different from the others.
أنها مختلفة قليلاً عن الأخريات.
Mounds visualizes the entire dataset as large, gelatinous blobs
تقوم تلال بجعل قاعدة البيانات مرئية كنقاط كبيرة جلاتينية
which kind of jiggle.
التي هي نوع من الهزهزة.
And if I hold down my cursor, they do a little dance.
واذا أمسكت بمؤشري، تقوم بقليل من الرقص.
We see "better" is the most frequent feeling, followed by "bad."
تشاهدون "أفضل" هو أكثر المشاعر ظهوراً، يعقبه "سيئ".
And then if I go over here, the list begins to scroll,
وبعد ذلك اذا ذهبت الى هنا، تبدأ القائمة بالتمرير،
and there are actually thousands of feelings that have been collected.
وهناك في الواقع آلالاف المشاعر التي تم تجميعها.
You can see the little pink cursor moving along,
يمكنكم رؤية المؤشر الوردي يتحرك ،
representing our position.
يمثل وضعنا.
Here we see people that feel "slipping," "nauseous," "responsible."
كيف نرى الناس الذين يشعرون ب"الإنزلاق،" القرف"، "المسئولية".
There's also a search capability,
هناك أيضاً إمكانية بحث،
if you're interested in finding out about a certain population.
اذا كنت تتشوق لمعرفة شئ حيال مجموعة محددة.
For instance, you could find women who feel "addicted"
كمثال، يمكنك إيجاد أمرأة تشعر ب" الإدمان"
in their 20s when it was cloudy in Bangladesh.
في العشرينات عندما كان الجو غائماً في بنغلاديش.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But I'll spare you that.
لكني سأوفر عليكم ذلك.
So here are some of my favorite montages that have been collected:
إذاً هنا بعض المونتاج المفضل لدي تم جمعها:
"I feel so much of my dad alive in me that there isn't even room for me."
"أشعر أن كثير من والدي يعيش داخلي بحيث لا يوجد مكان لي".
"I feel very lonely."
"أشعر بالوحدة الشديدة."
"I need to be in some backwoods redneck town
" أريد أن أكون في بلدة مأهولة متخلفة
so that I can feel beautiful."
بحيث أستطيع الشعور بالجمال."
"I feel invisible to you."
"أشعر أنني غير مرئي بالنسبة لك".
"I wouldn't hide it if society didn't make me feel like I needed to."
"لن أحجبها اذا لم يجعلني المجتمع أشعر بأنني بحاجة لذلك."
"I feel in love with Carolyn." "I feel so naughty."
أشعر بالحب تجاه كارولين." "أشعر بالبذاءة"
"I feel these weirdoes are actually an asset to college life."
أشعر أن هذه الأشياء الغريبة في الواقع هي الأصل الكلي للحياة."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
"I love how I feel today."
"أحب ما أشعر به اليوم."
So as you can see, We Feel Fine uses a technique
إذاً كما ترون اليوم، يستخدم "نشعر بتحسن" أسلوباً
that I call "passive observation."
أسميه أنا "الرقابة السلبية."
What I mean by that is that it passively observes people
ما أعنيه بذلك هو أنه يراقب الناس بسلبية
as they live their lives. It scans the world's blogs
كما يعيشون حياتهم. يقوم بمسح عالم المدونات
and looks at what people are writing,
وينظر في ما يكتبه الناس،
and these people don't know they're being watched or interviewed.
ولا يعلم هؤلاء الناس أنهم مراقبون أو يقابلهم أحد.
And because of that,
وبسبب ذلك،
you end up getting very honest, candid, sincere responses
تحصل في نهاية المطاف على ردود صادقة وصريحة جداً
that are often very moving.
التي تكون في العادة شاعرية.
And this is a technique that I usually prefer in my work
وهذا هو الأسلوب المفضل لدي في عملي
because people don't know they're being interviewed.
لأن الناس لا يعلمون أنهم مراقبون.
They're just living life, and they end up just acting like that.
يعيشون حياتهم فقط -- ويتعاملون هكذا في نهاية المطاف.
Another technique is directly questioning people.
أسلوب آخر هو سؤال الناس مباشرة.
And this is a technique that I explored in a different project,
وذلك الأسلوب الذي أستكشفه في مشروع مختلف،
the Yahoo! Time Capsule,
ياهو! كبسولة الزمن،
which was designed to take a fingerprint of the world in 2006.
الذي كان مخصصاً لأخذ بصمة أصبع للعالم عام 2006.
It was divided into ten very simple themes --
تم تقسيمه لعشرة مواضيع بسيطة جداً --
love, anger, sadness and so on --
الحب، الغضب، الحزن والخ --
each of which contained a single, very open-ended question
كلُ منها يحوي سؤال واحد مفتوح للغاية
put to the world: What do you love? What makes you angry?
موضوع للعالم: ماذا تحب؟ ما الذي يجعلك تغضب؟
What makes you sad? What do you believe in? And so on.
ما الذي يجعلك تحزن؟ في ماذا تعتقد؟ والخ.
The time capsule was available for one month online,
كبسولة الزمن كانت متاحة على الإنترنت لمدة شهر،
translated into 10 languages, and this is what it looked like.
تمت ترجمتها لعشرة لغات، وهكذا كانت تبدو.
It's a spinning globe,
أنه عالم معمور،
the surface of which is entirely composed of the pictures
السطح الذي يتألف بالكامل من الصور
and words and drawings of people
وكلمات ورسومات الناس
that submitted to the time capsule.
التي تم إرسالها لكبسولة الزمن.
The ten themes radiate out and orbit the time capsule.
المواضيع العشرة تشع وتدور في فلك كبسولة الزمن.
You can sift through this data and see what people have submitted.
يمكنك التدقيق فيها عبر هذه البيانات ونرى ما أرسله الناس .
This is in response to, What's beautiful? "Miss World."
هذا رد هلى ، ما هو الشئ الجميل؟ "ملكة جمال العالم."
There are two modes to the time capsule.
هناك وضعان لكبسولة الزمن.
There's One World, which presents the spinning globe,
هناك عالم واحد، يمثل الكون المعمور،
and Many Voices, which splits the data out into film strips
وعديد من الأصوات، التي تقسم البيانات الى أشرطة أفلام
and lets you sift through them one by one.
وتجعلك تدقق واحدة تلو الأخرى.
So this project was punctuated by a really amazing event,
إذاً هذا المشروع تخلله حدث مدهش حقاً
which was held in the desert outside Albuquerque in New Mexico
الذي تمت إقامته في الصحراء خارج البوكيرك في نيومكسيكو
at the Jemez Pueblo, where for three consecutive nights,
في جميز بيبلو، حيث لثلاث ليال متتالية،
the contents of the capsule were projected onto the sides
محتويات الكبسولة تم إسقاطها على جوانب
of the ancient Red Rock Canyon walls,
الجدران الصخرية الحمراء القديمة كانيون،
which stand about 200 feet tall. It was really incredible.
التي تعلو 200 قدم. كانت بالفعل لا تصدق.
And we also projected the contents of the time capsule
وأيضاً أسقطنا محتويات كبسولة الزمن
as binary code using a 35-watt laser into outer space.
كشفرة ثنائية بإستخدام 35 واط من الليزر الى الفضاء الخارجي.
You can see the orange line leaving the desert floor
يمكنك رؤية الخط البرتقالي يغادر سطح الصحراء
at about a 45 degree angle there. This was amazing
بزاوية مقدارها حوالي 45 درجة هناك. كان مدهشاً
because the first night I looked at all this information
لأن الليلة الأولى طالعت كل هذه المعلومات
and really started seeing the gaps that I talked about earlier --
وبدأت بالفعل رؤية الفوارق التي تحدثت عنها سلفاً --
the differences in age, gender and wealth and so on.
الفوارق العمرية، النوعية والثروة والخ.
But, you know, as I looked at this more and more and more,
لكن، تعرفون، كلما نظرت الى هذا مرة ومرتين وثلاثة،
and saw these images go across the rocks,
ورأيت تلك الصور تعبر الصخور،
I realized I was seeing the same archetypal events
أدركت أنني كنت أشاهد نفس الأحداث التوراتية
depicted again and again and again.
توصف مراراً وتكراراً.
You know: weddings, births, funerals, the first car, the first kiss,
تعرفون: الزواج، المواليد، الوفيات، السيارة الأولى، القبلة الأولى،
the first camel or horse -- depending on the culture.
أو جمل أو حصان -- إعتماداً على الثقافة.
And it was really moving. And this picture here was taken
وكان ذلك بالفعل عاطفياً. وهذه الصور تم إلتقاطها
the final night from a distant cliff about two miles away,
في الليلة الأخيرة من هاوية بعيدة حوالي ميلين،
where the contents of the capsule were being beamed into space.
حيث كانت محتويات الكبسولة تنتشر في الفضاء.
And there was something very moving
وكان هناك شئ مثير للعواطف بشدة
about all of this human expression being shot off into the night sky.
حول كل هذه المشاعر الإنسانية يتم إرسالها الى السماء.
And it started to make me think a lot about the night sky,
وبدأ ذلك يجعلني أفكر بالكثير من الأشياء حول سماء الليل،
and how humans have always used the night sky
وكيف أن البشر دائماً أستخدموا سماء الليل
to project their great stories.
ليشرعوا في قصصهم العظيمة.
You know, as a child in Vermont, on a farm where I grew up,
تعرفون، كطفل في فيرمونت، في مزرعة حيث نشأت،
I would often look up into the dark sky
أنظر الى السماء المظلمة دائماً
and see the three star belt of Orion, the Hunter.
وارى حزام النجوم ، الصياد.
And as an adult, I've been more aware
وكشخص راشد، كنت أكثر إدراكاً
of the great Greek myths playing out in the sky overhead every night.
بأساطير اليونان العظيمة باللعب في في السماء كل ليلة.
You know, Orion facing the roaring bull.
تعرفون، أورين تواجه خوار الثور.
Perseus flying to the rescue of Andromeda.
فرساوس يحلق لإنقاذ أندروميدا.
Zeus battling Chronos for control of Mount Olympus.
زيوس يقاتل كرونوس من أجل السيطرة على جبل أوليمبوس.
I mean, these are the great tales of the Greeks.
أعني، تلك الحكايات العظيمة لليونانيين.
And it caused me to wonder about our world today.
وتسببت في جعلي أتعجب حول عالمنا اليوم.
And it caused me to wonder specifically,
وجعلتني أستغرب تحديداً،
if we could make new constellations today,
لو استطعنا صنع تشكيلات جديدة اليوم ،
what would those look like? What would those be?
كيف سيكون شكلها؟ ماذا سيكونوا؟
If we could make new pictures in the sky, what would we draw?
اذا أستطعنا صنع صور جديدة في السماء، ماذا يمكن أن نرسم؟
What are the great stories of today?
ما هي القصص العظيمة لليوم؟
And those are the questions that inspired my new project,
وتلك الأسئلة ألهمت مشروعي الجديد،
which is debuting here today at TED.
الذي يظهر لأول مرة هنا في تيد.
Nobody's seen this yet, publicly.
لم يرى أي شخص هذا، علانية.
It's called Universe: Revealing Our Modern Mythology.
أنه يسمى الكون، يكشف لنا الأساطير الحديثة.
And it uses this metaphor of an interactive night sky.
وتستخدم هذا المجاز لسماء ليلة متفاعلة.
So, it's my great pleasure now to show this to you.
إذاً، أنه لشرف عظيم لي الآن أن أعرضه عليكم.
So, Universe will open here.
إذاً، الكون سيفتتح هنا.
And you'll see that it leads with a shifting star field,
وستشاهدوا أنه يُقاد مع ميدان نجمة متحول،
and there's an Aurora Borealis in the background,
وهناك الشفق القطبي في الخلفية،
kind of morphing with color. The color of the Aurora Borealis
نوع من التحوّر مع اللون. لون الشفق القطبي
can be controlled using this single bar of color at the bottom,
يمكن التحكم به بإستخدام شريط واحد من الألوان في الأسفل،
and we'll put it down here to red.
وسنقوم بوضعه أسفل هنا بالأحمر.
So you see this kind of -- these stars moving along.
إذاً يمكنكم رؤية نوع من -- هذه النجوم تمر على طول.
Now, these aren't just little points of light, little pixels.
الآن، هذه ليست نقاط صغيرة من الضوء الخافت.
Each of those stars actually represents
يعكس كلُ من هذه النجوم في الواقع
a specific event in the real world --
حدثاً محدداً في العالم الحقيقي --
a quote that was stated by somebody, an image,
إقتباس من شخص ما، صورة،
a news story, a person, a company. You know,
قصة جديدة، شخص، شركة. تعرفون،
some kind of heroic personality.
نوع ما من الشخصية البطولية.
And you might notice that as the cursor begins
وربما تلاحظون أنه بمجرد تحرك المؤشر
to touch some of these stars, that shapes begin to emerge.
ليلامس بعض هذه النجوم، يبدأ شكلها في التغير.
We see here there's a little man walking along, or maybe a woman.
نرى هنا أن هناك رجلاً يمشي على طول، أو ربما إمرأة.
And we see here a photograph with a head.
ونرى هنا، صورة برأس.
You can start to see words emerging here.
يمكنك رؤية الكلمات بدأت بالتغير هنا.
And those are
وتلك هي التشكيلات.
the constellations of today.
تلك هي تشكيلات اليوم.
And I can turn them all on,
ويمكنني تحويلهم ليعملوا،
and you can see them moving across the sky now.
ويمكنكم رؤيتهم يتحركون عبر السماء الآن.
This is the universe of 2007, the last two months.
هذا هو الكون عام 2007، الشهرين الأخيرين.
The data from this is global news coverage
البيانات من هذا هي تغطية الاخبار العالمية
from thousands of news sources around the world.
من آلالاف المصادر الإخبارية حول العالم.
It's using the API of a really great company that I work with
أنه يستخدم مكتبة لشركة عظيمة حقاً عملت معها
in New York, actually, called Daylife.
في نيويورك، في الواقع، تسمى داي لايف.
And it's kind of the zeitgeist view at this level
وهي نوع من وجهة نظرة روح العصر في هذا المستوى
of the world's current mythology over the last couple of months.
لأساطير العالم الحالية خلال الشهور القليلة الماضية
So we can see where it's emerging here, like President Ford,
إذاً يمكننا رؤية أين تتغير هنا، مثل الرئيس فورد،
Iraq, Bush. And we can actually isolate just the words --
العراق، بوش. يمكنكم في الواقع إختيار الكلمات --
I call them secrets -- and we can cause them to form
أسميهم "أسرار" -- ويمكننا جعلهم يشكلون
an alphabetical list. And we see Anna Nicole Smith
قائمة أبجدية. يمكننا رؤية آنا نيكلاي سميث
playing a big role recently.
تلعب دوراً بارزاً موخراً.
President Ford -- this is Gerald Ford's funeral.
الرئيس فورد -- هذه جنازة جيرالد فورد.
We can actually click anything in Universe
يمكننا في الواقع الضغط على أي شئ في "الكون"
and have it become the center of the universe,
وتصبح مركز الكون،
and everything else will enter its orbit.
وأي شئ آخر سيدخل في مداره.
So, we'll click Ford, and now that becomes the center.
إذاً، سنضغط على فورد، والآن يصبح في المركز.
And the things that relate to Ford enter its orbit
وكل شئ متعلق ب فورد سيدخل في مداره
and swirl around it.
ويحول حوله.
We can isolate just the photographs, and we now see those.
يمكننا إختيار فقط الصور، والآن نرى تلك.
We can click on one of those
يمكننا الضغط على أحدها
and have the photograph be the center of the universe.
والحصول على الصورة تصبح مركز الكون.
Now the things that relate to it are swirling around.
الآن الأشياء المرتبطة بها ستدور في المدار.
We can click on this and we see this iconic image
يمكنك الضغط على هذا وترى هذه الصورة الإيقونة
of Betty Ford kissing her husband's coffin.
ل بيتي فورد تقبل نعش زوجها.
In Universe, there's kind of no end. It just goes infinitely,
في "الكون"، هناك نوع من اللا نهاية. يذهب الى ما لا نهاية،
and you can just kind of click on stuff.
ويمكنك نوع ما الضغط على الأشياء.
This is a photographic representation, called Snapshots.
هذا التمثيل الصوري، يسمى لقطات.
But we can actually be more specific in defining our universe.
لكن يمكننا في الواقع أن نصبح أكثر تحديداً حينما نعرّف "كوننا".
So, if we want to,
إذاً، اذا رغبت في،
let's check out what Bill Clinton's universe looks like.
لنرى كيف يبدو "كون" بيل كلينتون.
And let's see, in the past week, what he's been up to.
ولنرى، في الأسبوع الماضي، ماذا كان يفعل.
So now, we have a new universe, which is just constrained
إذاً الآن، لدينا "كون" جديد، مقيد فقط
to all things Bill Clinton.
لكل الأشياء حول بيل كلينتون.
We can have his constellations emerge here.
يمكننا الحصول على هذه الأساطير تنشأ هنا.
We can pull out his secrets,
يمكننا سحب أسراره،
and we see that it has a lot to do with candidates,
يمكننا رؤية أن لديه الكثير ليفعله مع المشرحين،
Hillary, presidential, Barack Obama.
هيلاري، الرئاسة، باراك أوباما.
We can see the stories
يمكننا رؤية القصص
that Bill Clinton is taking part in right now.
بأن بيل كلينتون يشارك الآن.
Any of those can be opened up.
أيُ من تلك يمكن فتحها.
So we see Obama and the Clintons meet in Alabama.
إذاً يمكننا رؤية أوباما وكلينتون يلتقيان في ألاباما.
You can see that this is an important story;
يمكنكم رؤية أن هذه قصة مهمة.
there are a lot of things in its orbit. If we open this up,
هناك الكثير من الأشياء في مداره. اذا فتحنا هذه،
we get different perspectives on this story.
نتلقى نظرات مختلفة حول هذه القصة.
You can click any of those to go out and read the article
يمكنك الضغط على أي من تلك للذهاب وقرأة المقال
at the source. This one's from Al Jazeera.
في المصدر. هذا الخبر من الجزيرة.
We can also see the superstars. These would be the people
يمكننا أيضاً رؤية النجوم. هذه ستكون الناس
that are kind of the looming heroes and heroines
الذين يلوحون في الأفق كأبطال وبطلات
in the universe of Bill Clinton. So there's Bill Clinton, Hillary,
في "كون" بيل كلينتون. إذاً هناك بيل كلينتون، هيلاري،
Iraq, George Bush, Barack Obama, Scooter Libby --
العراق، جورج بوش، باراك أوباما، سكوتر ليبي --
these are kind of the people of Bill Clinton.
هؤلاء نوع ما مصاحبة ل بيل كلينتون.
We can also see a world map, so this shows us the geographic reach
يمكننا أيضاً رؤية خارطة العالم، إذاً يظهر هذا الوصول الجغرافي
of Bill Clinton in the last week or so.
لبيل كلينتون في الأسبوع الماضي .
We can see he's been focused in America
ستلاحظون أنه يركز على أمريكا
because he's been campaigning, probably,
لأنه من المرجح أنه في الحملة الإنتخابية،
but a little bit of action over here in the Middle East.
لكن القليل من الحركة هنا في الشرق الأوسط.
And then we can also see a timeline.
وبعد ذلك يمكننا أيضاً رؤية الخط الزمني.
So we see that he was a bit quiet on Saturday,
إذاً نرى أنه كان هادئاً يوم السبت،
but he was back to work on Sunday morning,
لكنه عاد للعمل في صباح الأحد،
and actually been tapering off since then this week.
وبالفعل تفتق منذ ذلك الوقت هذا الأسبوع.
And it's not limited to just people or dates,
وليس قاصراً فقط على الناس أو التواريخ،
but we can actually put in concepts also.
لكن يمكن أيضاً وضعه في سياق المفاهيم.
So if I put in climate change for all of 2006,
إذاً اذا وضعت تغير المناخ لكل عام 2006،
we'll see what that universe looks like.
سترى كيف كان يبدو الكون حينها.
Here we have our star field. Here we have our shapes.
لدينا هنا ميدان النجوم، لدينا هنا أشكالنا،
Here we have our secrets.
لدينا هنا أسرارنا.
So we see again, climate change is large:
إذاً نرى مجدداً، تغير المناخ مكبّر.
Nairobi, global conference, environmental.
نيروبي، المؤتمر الدولي، البيئي.
And there are also quotes that you can see,
وهناك أيضاً إقتباسات يمكنكم رؤيتها،
if you're interested in reading about quotes on climate change.
اذا كنتم مهتمين بإقتباسات حول تغير المناخ.
You know, this is really an infinite thing.
تعرفون، هذا بالفعل شئ لا نهائي.
The superstars of climate change in 2006:
نجوم تغير المناخ لعام 2006:
United States, Britain, China. You know,
الولايات المتحدة، بريطانيا، الصين. تعرفون،
these are the towering countries that kind of define this concept.
هذه الدول الأكثر إحاطةً بنوع ما من تعريف هذا المفهوم.
So this is a piece that demands exploration.
إذاً هذه قطعة تحتاج لإستكشاف.
This will be online in several days, probably next Tuesday.
سيكون متاحاً على الإنترنت بعد بضعة أيام، من المرجح الثلاثاء القادم.
And you'll all be able to use it and kind of explore
وسيكون بمقدوركم إستخدامه وإستكشاف
what your own personal mythology might be.
ما قد ستكون عليه أساطيركم الشخصية .
You'll notice that in Daylife -- rather, in Universe --
ستلاحظون أن داى لايف -- بدلاً، في "الكون"،
it supports both the notion of a global mythology,
تدعم كلا من فكرة وجود الأساطير العالمية ،
which is represented by something as broad as, say, 2007,
والتي تم تمثيلها بشئ واسع مثل عام 2007،
and also a personal mythology.
وأيضاً الأساطير الشخصية.
As you search for the things that are important to you in your world,
وتقوم بالبحث عن أشياء أكثر أهمية لك في عالمك،
and then see what the constellations of those might look like.
وحينها يمكنكم رؤية ما قد تكون عليه تلك الأساطير.
So it's been a pleasure. Thank you very much.
إذاً فقد كان من دواعي سروري، شكراً جزيلاً لكم. وشكراً.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)